I can't hold on to religious beliefs
Sunim, I'm not an atheist.
I believe religions are
essential to human beings.
I've attended
Buddhist temples with my parents.
I've also tried attending
Protestant and Catholic churches.
And yet I'm unable to fall
deeply into a certain religion.
I think religion can be a great thing
to rely on when in hard times.
I wonder if it's wrong to think this way,
and if I should give up trying
to believe in a religion.
(Sunim) You're thinking wrong.
(Audience Laughter)
(Questioner Laugher)
I'll tell you why.
You shouldn't force yourself
to believe in something.
Only believe in what you can believe.
They say Buddha walked seven steps
as soon as he was born.
Whether you believe in this or not
is not important.
The story simply symbolizes things.
Do you understand?
The fact that he stood up
the moment he was born
represents how he was
the owner of his own destiny.
The fact that Buddha walked
7 steps means that
he transcended the 6 realms,
the cycle of life.
Myths of virgin births mean
a certain thing too.
In the old days, a king would pass
on his throne to a son,
an aristocrat would pass on his title.
Hence a virgin birth usually
indicates that a person was
self-made without a hereditary title.
For example, Jumong didn't
succeed his father's position,
he founded Goguryeo all on his own.
Hence myths say
he was born a virgin birth.
In Manchu myths,
a virgin eats a fruit that a crow
dropped and gives birth.
In another story, a woman gives birth
after a snake coils around her body.
Such myths usually indicate
self-made people.
What's important is to focus
on the core message of these stories.
Whether you literally believe in
these stories or not isn't important.
What's important is to know
what the stories imply.
Religion isn't about forcing yourself
to believe in things you can't believe.
Also theoretically speaking,
you sow what you reap, do you not?
You have to do good to receive good.
You don't receive good unless
you've done good yourself.
If you say otherwise and call
that religion, that's nonsense.
Young people shouldn't
believe in such ideas.
What we can believe in
are things like this :
If a mother is hot tempered
around a child,
the child is bound
to have a hot temper too.
Hence should a mother lose her temper
with her child? She shouldn't.
Only then can the child
become good-natured.
If a woman was once hot tempered
and yet changed herself
for the sake of her child,
has she improved herself or not?
(Questioner) She has.
(Sunim) Yes, she has.
She has become a better person,
the child has turned out for the better.
If you bear hatred towards your husband,
it means you hate him
because he's a bad person.
This makes your child a child of
a bad person, does it not?
Then will your child ever
become great? No he/she won't.
This is why a mother should not bear
hatred towards her husband.
If she does, it will harm the child.
What about a grandmother
raising a grandchild
bearing hatred towards
her daughter-in-law?
The grandchild will not turn out great.
And yet we're ignorant and do things
that would eventually come to harm us.
To realize such foolishness
and prevent badness,
this we call a life of wisdom.
Christ actually taught us
such things himself.
If you read the Bible carefully,
the concept of believers going to heaven
vs non-believers going to hell has
nothing to do with Christ's teachings.
Neither do Buddhist scriptures say that
you'll have good fortune
if you pray a certain way.
Buddha, Christ, Confucius, Zhuangzi
all seeked to explain
the principles of life.
If you live wisely by these principles,
your sufferings in life would diminish.
This is religion at it's core.
Faith itself is not what's important.
The crux of religion is
to become rightfully aware
of the true principles of life.
What we mention as unconditional belief
this is blind faith and superstition.
Blind faith doesn't make
you a religious person.
A religious person should
believe in the truth.
(Sunim) Do you understand?
(Questioner) Yes.
Hence a Buddhist should believe
in the teachings of Buddha,
not in Buddha himself.
You shouldn't believe in teachings
because you think you should.
Faith comes when teachings
logically make sense to you.
To think 'I should believe
in Buddha' is not true faith.
Once his teachings logically make sense
to you, you start believing.
So if you're only a believer
because I say so, that is superstition.
Instead, if my words make sense to you
and you actually resolve your life issues
by following them,
you'd start believing.
This we call faith.
Hence you shouldn't force yourself
to believe in anything.
Just believe in what makes sense to you.
(Questioner) Thank you.
You're welcome.